It's often said that you can tell a lot about a person by looking at what's on their bookshelves. What do my bookshelves say about me? Well, when I asked myself this question a few years ago, I made an alarming discovery. I'd always thought of myself as a fairly cultured, cosmopolitan sort of person. But my bookshelves told a rather different story. Pretty much all the titles on them were by British or North American authors, and there was almost nothing in translation. Discovering this massive, cultural blind spot in my reading came as quite a shock. And when I thought about it, it seemed like a real shame. I knew there had to be lots of amazing stories out there by writers working in languages other than English. And it seemed really sad to think that my reading habits meant I would probably never encounter them. So, I decided to prescribe myself an intensive course of global reading. 2012 was set to be a very international year for the UK; it was the year of the London Olympics. And so I decided to use it as my time frame to try to read a novel, short story collection or memoir from every country in the world. And so I did. And it was very exciting and I learned some remarkable things and made some wonderful connections that I want to share with you today. But it started with some practical problems. After I'd worked out which of the many different lists of countries in the world to use for my project, I ended up going with the list of UN-recognized nations, to which I added Taiwan, which gave me a total of 196 countries. And after I'd worked out how to fit reading and blogging about, roughly, four books a week around working five days a week, I then had to face up to the fact that I might even not be able to get books in English from every country. Only around 4.5 percent of the literary works published each year in the UK are translations, and the figures are similar for much of the English-speaking world. Although, the proportion of translated books published in many other countries is a lot higher. 4.5 percent is tiny enough to start with, but what that figure doesn't tell you is that many of those books will come from countries with strong publishing networks and lots of industry professionals primed to go out and sell those titles to English-language publishers. So, for example, although well over 100 books are translated from French and published in the UK each year, most of them will come from countries like France or Switzerland. French-speaking Africa, on the other hand, will rarely ever get a look-in. The upshot is that there are actually quite a lot of nations that may have little or even no commercially available literature in English. Their books remain invisible to readers of the world's most published language. But when it came to reading the world, the biggest challenge of all for me was that fact that I didn't know where to start. Having spent my life reading almost exclusively British and North American books, I had no idea how to go about sourcing and finding stories and choosing them from much of the rest of the world. I couldn't tell you how to source a story from Swaziland. I wouldn't know a good novel from Namibia. There was no hiding it -- I was a clueless literary xenophobe. So how on earth was I going to read the world? I was going to have to ask for help. So in October 2011, I registered my blog, ayearofreadingtheworld.com, and I posted a short appeal online. I explained who I was, how narrow my reading had been, and I asked anyone who cared to to leave a message suggesting what I might read from other parts of the planet. Now, I had no idea whether anyone would be interested, but within a few hours of me posting that appeal online, people started to get in touch. At first, it was friends and colleagues. Then it was friends of friends. And pretty soon, it was strangers. Four days after I put that appeal online, I got a message from a woman called Rafidah in Kuala Lumpur. She said she loved the sound of my project, could she go to her local English-language bookshop and choose my Malaysian book and post it to me? I accepted enthusiastically, and a few weeks later, a package arrived containing not one, but two books -- Rafidah's choice from Malaysia, and a book from Singapore that she had also picked out for me. Now, at the time, I was amazed that a stranger more than 6,000 miles away would go to such lengths to help someone she would probably never meet. But Rafidah's kindness proved to be the pattern for that year. Time and again, people went out of their way to help me. Some took on research on my behalf, and others made detours on holidays and business trips to go to bookshops for me. It turns out, if you want to read the world, if you want to encounter it with an open mind, the world will help you. When it came to countries with little or no commercially available literature in English, people went further still. Books often came from surprising sources. My Panamanian read, for example, came through a conversation I had with the Panama Canal on Twitter. Yes, the Panama Canal has a Twitter account. And when I tweeted at it about my project, it suggested that I might like to try and get hold of the work of the Panamanian author Juan David Morgan. I found Morgan's website and I sent him a message, asking if any of his Spanish-language novels had been translated into English. And he said that nothing had been published, but he did have an unpublished translation of his novel "The Golden Horse." He emailed this to me, allowing me to become one of the first people ever to read that book in English. Morgan was by no means the only wordsmith to share his work with me in this way. From Sweden to Palau, writers and translators sent me self-published books and unpublished manuscripts of books that hadn't been picked up by Anglophone publishers or that were no longer available, giving me privileged glimpses of some remarkable imaginary worlds. I read, for example, about the Southern African king Ngungunhane, who led the resistance against the Portuguese in the 19th century; and about marriage rituals in a remote village on the shores of the Caspian sea in Turkmenistan. I met Kuwait's answer to Bridget Jones. (Laughter) And I read about an orgy in a tree in Angola. But perhaps the most amazing example of the lengths that people were prepared to go to to help me read the world, came towards the end of my quest, when I tried to get hold of a book from the tiny, Portuguese-speaking African island nation of São Tomé and Príncipe. Now, having spent several months trying everything I could think of to find a book that had been translated into English from the nation, it seemed as though the only option left to me was to see if I could get something translated for me from scratch. Now, I was really dubious whether anyone was going to want to help with this, and give up their time for something like that. But, within a week of me putting a call out on Twitter and Facebook for Portuguese speakers, I had more people than I could involve in the project, including Margaret Jull Costa, a leader in her field, who has translated the work of Nobel Prize winner José Saramago. With my nine volunteers in place, I managed to find a book by a São Toméan author that I could buy enough copies of online. Here's one of them. And I sent a copy out to each of my volunteers. They all took on a couple of short stories from this collection, stuck to their word, sent their translations back to me, and within six weeks, I had the entire book to read. In that case, as I found so often during my year of reading the world, my not knowing and being open about my limitations had become a big opportunity. When it came to São Tomé and Príncipe, it was a chance not only to learn something new and discover a new collection of stories, but also to bring together a group of people and facilitate a joint creative endeavor. My weakness had become the project's strength. The books I read that year opened my eyes to many things. As those who enjoy reading will know, books have an extraordinary power to take you out of yourself and into someone else's mindset, so that, for a while at least, you look at the world through different eyes. That can be an uncomfortable experience, particularly if you're reading a book from a culture that may have quite different values to your own. But it can also be really enlightening. Wrestling with unfamiliar ideas can help clarify your own thinking. And it can also show up blind spots in the way you might have been looking at the world. When I looked back at much of the English-language literature I'd grown up with, for example, I began to see how narrow a lot of it was, compared to the richness that the world has to offer. And as the pages turned, something else started to happen, too. Little by little, that long list of countries that I'd started the year with, changed from a rather dry, academic register of place names into living, breathing entities. Now, I don't want to suggest that it's at all possible to get a rounded picture of a country simply by reading one book. But cumulatively, the stories I read that year made me more alive than ever before to the richness, diversity and complexity of our remarkable planet. It was as though the world's stories and the people who'd gone to such lengths to help me read them had made it real to me. These days, when I look at my bookshelves or consider the works on my e-reader, they tell a rather different story. It's the story of the power books have to connect us across political, geographical, cultural, social, religious divides. It's the tale of the potential human beings have to work together. And, it's testament to the extraordinary times we live in, where, thanks to the Internet, it's easier than ever before for a stranger to share a story, a worldview, a book with someone she may never meet, on the other side of the planet. I hope it's a story I'm reading for many years to come. And I hope many more people will join me. If we all read more widely, there'd be more incentive for publishers to translate more books, and we would all be richer for that. Thank you. (Applause)
A menudo se dice que se puede saber mucho sobre una persona al ver lo que está en sus libreros. ¿Qué dicen mis libreros de mí? Bueno, cuando me hice esta pregunta hace unos años, hice un descubrimiento alarmante. Siempre me había visto como alguien bastante culta y cosmopolita. Pero mis librerías contaban una historia bastante diferente. Prácticamente todos los títulos eran de autores británicos o norteamericanos, y no había casi nada traducido. El descubrimiento de este masivo punto ciego cultural en mis lecturas me dejó en shock. Y cuando pensé en ello, me pareció una verdadera lástima. Sabía que tenía que haber muchas historias increíbles por ahí de escritores que escriben en lenguas diferentes al inglés. Y parecía muy triste pensar que por mis hábitos de lectura probablemente nunca me toparía con ellos. Así que decidí automedicarme un curso intensivo de lectura global. El 2012 se pensó para ser un año muy internacional para el Reino Unido; fue el año de los Juegos Olímpicos de Londres. Así que decidí utilizarlo como mi calendario para tratar de leer una novela, una colección de cuentos o una memoria de todos los países del mundo. Y así lo hice. Y fue muy emocionante y aprendí algunas cosas notables e hice algunas conexiones maravillosas que quiero compartirles hoy. Pero comenzó con algunos problemas prácticos. Después de haber decidido cuál de las diversas listas de países en el mundo usar para mi proyecto, terminé siguiendo la lista de naciones reconocidas por la ONU, a la que añadí Taiwán, que me dio un total de 196 países. Y después de haber resuelto cómo ajustar la lectura y bloggeo de aproximadamente, cuatro libros a la semana trabajando cerca de cinco días a la semana, entonces tuve que enfrentar el hecho de que incluso no podría ser capaz de conseguir libros en inglés de todos los países. Solo alrededor de un 4.5% de las obras literarias publicadas cada año en el Reino Unido son traducciones y las cifras son similares para gran parte del mundo de habla inglesa. Sin embargo, la proporción de publicaciones de libros traducidos en muchos otros países es mucho más alta. 4.5% es lo suficientemente pequeño para empezar, pero lo que esa cifra no dice es que muchos de esos libros vendrán de países con fuertes redes editoriales y muchos profesionales de la industria preparados para salir a vender esos títulos a las editoriales en idioma inglés. Así, por ejemplo, aunque poco más de 100 libros se traducen del francés y se publican cada año en el Reino Unido la mayoría de ellos vendrán de países como Francia o Suiza. Por otro lado, la África de habla francesa, rara vez se tendrá en cuenta. El resultado es que hay muchas naciones que pueden tener poca o ninguna literatura comercial en inglés disponible. Sus libros siguen siendo invisibles para los lectores del lenguaje con más publicaciones del mundo. Pero cuando se trataba de leer el mundo, el mayor reto de todos para mí fue el hecho de no saber por dónde empezar. Después de haber pasado la vida leyendo casi exclusivamente libros británicos y de norteamérica no tenía idea de cómo conseguir y encontrar historias y escogerlas entre muchas del resto del mundo. No podría decidir cómo conseguir una historia de Swazilandia. No conocía una buena novela de Namibia. No podía ocultarlo: Era una xenófoba literaria sin idea. Entonces, ¿cómo era posible que yo fuera a leer el mundo? Iba a tener que pedir ayuda. Así, en octubre de 2011, registré mi blog, ayearofreadingtheworld.com, y publiqué una corta petición en línea. Expliqué quién era, lo cerrada que había sido mi lectura, y pedí a quien quisiera que dejara un mensaje sugiriendo qué podría leer de otras partes del planeta. Ahora bien, no tenía ni idea si alguien estaría interesado, pero luego de unas cuantas horas de publicar mi petición en línea, la gente empezó a ponerse en contacto. Al principio, eran amigos y colegas. Luego eran amigos de mis amigos. Y muy pronto, fueron extraños. Cuatro días después de poner mi petición en línea, recibí un mensaje de una mujer llamada Rafidah en Kuala Lumpur. Me dijo que le encantaba cómo sonaba mi proyecto y que podría ir a su librería local de libros en inglés y escoger mi libro de Malasia y enviármelo. Acepté con entusiasmo, y unas semanas más tarde, llegó un paquete con no uno, sino dos libros, la elección de Rafidah de Malasia, y un libro de Singapur que también había elegido para mí. En ese momento, me sorprendió que un extraño a casi 10 mil km. de distancia fuera tan lejos para ayudar a alguien que probablemente nunca conocería. Pero la bondad de Rafidah resultó ser el patrón en ese año. Una y otra vez, la gente hacía lo posible para ayudarme. Algunos se dieron a la investigación en mi nombre y otros hicieron desvíos en vacaciones y viajes de negocios para ir a las librerías por mí. Resulta que, si quieres leer el mundo, si quieres encontrarlo con mente abierta, el mundo te ayudará. Cuando se trataba de países con poca o ninguna literatura comercial en inglés disponible las personas fueron aún más lejos. A menudo los libros provenían de fuentes sorprendentes. Mi lectura de Panamá, por ejemplo, vino a través de una conversación que tuve en Twitter con el Canal de Panamá Sí, el Canal de Panamá tiene una cuenta de Twitter. Y cuando le envié un Tweet sobre mi proyecto, sugirió qué podría probar conseguir el trabajo del autor panameño Juan David Morgan. Encontré el sitio web de Morgan y le envié un mensaje, preguntando si alguna de sus Novelas en español se habían traducido al inglés. Me respondió que no había nada publicado, pero tenía una traducción inédita de su novela "El Caballo de Oro". Me la envió por correo electrónico lo que me permitió ser una de las primeras personas en leer ese libro en inglés. Morgan no fue de ninguna manera el único escritor en compartir su trabajo conmigo de esta forma. De Suecia a Palau, escritores y traductores me enviaron libros publicados individualmente y manuscritos inéditos de libros que rechazaban las editoriales de habla inglesa o que ya no estaban disponibles, dándome atisbos privilegiados de algunos mundos imaginarios notables. Leí, por ejemplo, sobre el rey de África Austral Ngungunhane, que lideró la resistencia contra los portugueses en el siglo XIX; y sobre los rituales matrimoniales en una aldea remota a orillas del Mar Caspio en Turkmenistán. Conocí la respuesta de Kuwait para Bridget Jones. (Risas) Y leí sobre una orgía en un árbol en Angola. Pero tal vez el ejemplo más sorprendente de las molestias que las personas estaban dispuestas a tomar para ayudarme a leer el mundo, llegó hacia el final de mi búsqueda, cuando buscaba un libro de la pequeña nación insular africana de habla portuguesa Santo Tomé y Príncipe. Después de haber pasado varios meses intentando todo lo que pude para encontrar un libro traducido al inglés de esta nación, parecía que la única opción que me quedaba era ver si podía conseguir algo traducido para mí desde cero. Realmente dudaba si alguien iba a querer ayudar con esto, y renunciar a su tiempo para algo así. Pero, tras una semana de hacer un llamado en Twitter y Facebook para hablantes de portugués, tenía más gente de la que podía involucrar en el proyecto, incluyendo a Margaret Jull Costa, una líder en su campo, que ha traducido la obra del Premio Nobel José Saramago. Con mis nueve voluntarios listos, me las arreglé para encontrar un libro de un autor de Santo Tomé del que podía comprar suficientes copias en línea. Aquí está uno. Envié una copia a a cada una de mis voluntarios. Todos tomaron un par de historias cortas de esta colección, trabajaron, me enviaron sus traducciones, y al cabo de seis semanas, tenía todo el libro para leer. En ese caso, y como me ocurrió tan a menudo durante ese año, mi falta de conocimiento y el estar abierta acerca de mis limitaciones se habían convertido en una gran oportunidad. En el caso de Santo Tomé y Príncipe, fue una oportunidad no solo para aprender algo nuevo y descubrir una nueva colección de historias, sino también para reunir un grupo de personas y facilitar un esfuerzo creativo conjunto. Mi debilidad se había convertido en la fortaleza del proyecto. Los libros que leí ese año me abrieron los ojos a muchas cosas. Como quienes disfrutan de la lectura sabrán, los libros tienen el poder extraordinario de llevarte fuera de ti mismo y ponerte en la mente de alguien más, de modo que, durante un tiempo al menos, miras el mundo a través de los ojos de alguien más. Esa puede ser una experiencia incómoda, especialmente si estás leyendo un libro de una cultura que puede tener valores bastante diferentes a los tuyos. Pero también puede ser muy esclarecedor. Luchar con ideas poco familiares ayuda a clarificar tu propio pensamiento. Y también puede mostrarte puntos ciegos en la forma en que podrías haber estado mirando al mundo. Cuando volví a la literatura en inglés con la que había crecido, por ejemplo, empecé a ver lo estrecha que era mucha de ella, en comparación con la riqueza que el mundo tiene para ofrecer. Y a medida que pasaba las páginas, también comenzó a suceder algo. Poco a poco, esa larga lista de país con la que había empezado el año, pasó de un registro de nombres de lugares más bien seco y académico a uno de entidades vivas que respiran. No quiero sugerir que es en forma alguna posible obtener una imagen redondeada de un país simplemente leyendo un libro. Pero acumulativamente, las historias que leí ese año me hicieron más conciente que nunca de la riqueza, diversidad y complejidad de nuestro notable planeta. Era como si las historias del mundo y las personas que habían llegado a tales extremos para ayudarme a leerlos lo hubieran hecho real para mí. Hoy en día, cuando veo mis estanterías o miro las obras en mi e-reader, me cuentan una historia muy diferente. Es la historia del poder que tienen los libros para conectarnos a través de divisiones políticas, geográficas, religiosas, sociales, culturales. Es sobre el potencial en el que tienen que trabajar juntos los seres humanos. Su testamento a los tiempos extraordinarios en que vivimos en donde, gracias a la Internet, es más fácil que nunca para un extraño compartir una historia, una visión del mundo, un libro con alguien que tal vez nunca conocerá, al otro lado del planeta. Espero que sea una historia que leeré durante muchos años por venir y espero que mucha más gente me siga. Si todos leemos más ampliamente, los editores tendrían más incentivos para traducir más libros, y todos nos enriqueceríamos por eso. Gracias. (Aplausos)